Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is פ"א, Pei Alef,
and we pick up with where were we, we pick up well
in the middle of פ"א Pei Alef and it
is אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, right, it's the word starts with בכוסות,
bekosot, it's almost exactly in the middle, the line starts with בכוסות,
bekosot, I guess about 15 lines down, and it's אמר אביי. Amar
Abaye. So we just had a long discussion about, you know, this
whole thing about when the bloods get mixed up. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says put it on the top, put it on the bottom,
sort of every time you're doing the wrong place for some of
the blood, pretend as if the bad blood, haha, anyway, the wrong
blood is water, the חכמים chachamim don't buy this, pretend if it's
water, they don't allow you to לכתחילה l'chat'chila put it in the
wrong place even if you needed to do it that way in
order to make the קרבן korban valid, but if בדיעבד b'diavad you
did it, they'll admit that it worked. Anyway, throughout that entire debate
of course the simple sense is that we assume that the blood
is equally dispersed and wherever you put the blood you can assume
it's a mixture, which is the principle of יש בילה, yesh bila,
but the גמרא gemara was motivated because of some statement of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by water of a חטאת chatas of the פרה
אדומה parah adumah to try to say maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
holds אין בילה, ein bila, you can't assume equal distribution, and then
did some somersaults to try to fit that into those statements because
those statements certainly make it sound like wherever you're putting the blood,
there's a mixture of both. In the end, the גמרא gemara sort
of said well if we have to try to reinterpret those statements,
we'll assume that it's not talking that the blood's got mixed up
but the various bowls got mixed up and therefore you're very specifically
putting from each bowl, so you know you're putting from both bloods
in both places. Alright, so now the גמרא gemara now continues and
it gets to a side point that was addressed in this debate
but is implicit sort of was implicit and is interesting in its
own right. So the גמרא gemara says like this: אמר אביי לא
שנו אלא תחילת החטאת ועולה. Amar Abaye, lo shanu ella t'chilas hachattas
v'olah.
We're talking about when you're putting it,
you know when we're talking about the debate of what to do
is when you've got the blood that initially has to go up
for the חטאת chattas and has to go at the top of
the altar and the blood that initially has to go for the
עולה olah and has to go at the bottom of the altar
and they get mixed up, so anywhere you put it it's going
to be wrong for one. Okay, אבל סוף חטאת ועולה דברי הכל
מקום עולה מקום שיריים. aval sof chattas v'olah, divrei hakol makom olah
makom shirayim.
There's sort of like a comma after the word סוף, sof, after
the word חטאת, chattas, it's not סוף חטאת sof chattas and סוף
עולה, sof olah, it's סוף חטאת sof chattas comma ועולה. v'olah. If
you have blood that is the remainder of a חטאת, chattas, you
put the blood at the top of the altar and now you've
got the שיריים shirayim of a חטאת chattas and you mix those
in with the עולה olah blood, everybody would agree even the חכמים
chachamim would agree לכתחילה l'chat'chila put it at the bottom, it's the
right place for the עולה olah blood and the right place for
the end of the חטאת chattas blood, and that was implicit basically
in a ברייתא brayta that we quoted because a ברייתא brayta that
we quoted said that if you didn't ask him you put it
at the top, the חכמים chachamim agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that you can לכתחילה l'chat'chila put the remainder of the blood at
the bottom. Well why can you do that? What about the what
about the חטאת chattas blood? Well the answer is well yes that's
also where the חטאת chattas blood belongs once you've put the חטאת
chattas blood at the top. Okay, now the חידוש chiddush here is
as we're going to see in a minute is that when you
put the עולה olah blood you throw it at the walls of
the altar, you know sort of at a corner which hits two
walls, and when you spill the שיריים shirayim you're supposed to spill
it at the base. Now if it hits the walls, a, it's
in the lower half, conceptually we focus top half bottom half, so
it's the right half, and b, it'll run to the base, but
it doesn't get spilled directly to the base. So that's the חידוש.
chiddush. Meaning in
this case, so the חידוש chiddush is that that's okay you know
when it's considered to still be put at the right place, maybe
not the A plus plus place but whatever, but it's still you
know it's not the wrong place, it's right enough and therefore that's
okay if in this case for the mixture to put it throw
it at the wall, the חטאת chattas the remainder of the חטאת
chattas blood. Okay, so that's what he says. דברי הכל מקום עולה
מקום שיריים.
Divrei hakol makom olah
makom shirayim.
The place you put the עולה olah is an acceptable place meaning
the walls and the lower half to put the remnants of the
blood. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said back to אביי, Abaye, רב יוסף Rav Yosef who was אביי
Abaye's רבי, rebbi, הכי אמר רב יהודה, hachi amar Rav Yehuda, no,
I'm sorry, here's what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said, שיריים צריכים אצטבא,
shirayim t'richim itztaba,
that the שיריים shirayim the remnant of the blood needs like a
platform, meaning you have to pour it straight on the you know
sort of the horizontal base. You don't put it on a wall,
you don't put it on like on a vertical surface, you have
to pour it on a horizontal on a foundation. So even if
it runs to the base, that's not considered שפיכת שיריים. shfichas shirayim.
וכן אמר רבי שמעון, V'chein amar Rabbi Shimon,
and similarly said רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon like אביי, Abaye, not like
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, לא שנו אלא תחילת החטאת ועולה. lo shanu
ella t'chilas hachattas v'olah.
This is only the initial blood of a חטאת chattas mixed in
with the blood of an עולה. olah. אבל סוף חטאת ועולה, Aval
sof hachattas v'olah, but the end blood of a חטאת, chattas, the
שיריים shirayim of a חטאת chattas mixed with an עולה, olah, דברי
הכל מקום עולה מקום שיריים. divrei hakol makom olah makom shirayim. Everybody
would say לכתחילה l'chat'chila you could put it on the wall on
the bottom half and that is an acceptable place to put the
remnants of the blood. אמר רבי יוחנן ואיתימא רבי אליעזר עדיין היא
מחלוקת. Amar Rabbi Yochanan v'isayma Rabbi Eliezer, adayin hi machlokes. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan now backing up רב יוסף Rav Yosef says nope, this
is still a debate, they still debate this, the חכמים chachamim would
say better to spill it out into the you know into the
sort of like. the drain because this is not an acceptable place
to put the שריים. shrayim. Okay, fine. So that's the debate. Do
they agree or not in this case? מתיב רב הונא בר יהודה.
Mative Rav Huna bar Yehuda. קודש הם. Kodesh hem. So now we
have a פסוק pasuk that says by בכור, bechor, right, the פסוק
pasuk says that as you know, where רש"י Rashi quotes the whole
פסוק, pasuk, where is it?
Numbers
18:17, although I don't have a חומש Chumash here, anyway, את דמם
תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר, et damam tizrok al hamizbeach v'et
chelvam taktira, no is that the פסוק? pasuk? Hold on, I'm sorry.
What is it? Numbers 18:17?
Yeah, you want me to get you?
I got it, I'll use it. Here it is, over here too.
אך בכור שור או בכור כשב או בכור עז לא תפדה קודש
הם. את דמם תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר.
Ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez lo tifdeh kodesh
hem. Et damam tizrok al hamizbeach
v'et chelvam taktira.
Thank you. There you go, yeah, also
thank you.
אך בכור שור
או בכור כשב או בכור עז לא תפדה קודש הם. את דמם
תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר.
Ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez lo tifdeh kodesh
hem. Et
damam tizrok
al hamizbeach v'et chelvam taktira. So that's by the way where we
get the idea that the blood of the בכור bechor has one
application, but it says קודש הם, kodesh hem, they, the bloods, are
קודש. kodesh. Okay, what does that come to tell you? שאם נתערב
בדם קדשים אחרים יקרבו. She'im nitarav b'dam kadshim acherim yikreivu.
הם Hem in the plural means that they don't lose their identity
and even if they're mixed up with other bloods, you can still
put them on the altar. Okay, which is basically the principle we've
been dealing with, meaning we've dealt with technical questions if the bloods
go in the different places and so on, but we've never questioned
the idea that if they all belong in the right place or
whatever there should be a problem, which is basically what the גמרא
Gemara is going to question. What's the חידוש chiddush of this? To
tell me that if it's mixed up? There's got to be some
חידוש. chiddush. Okay, if they all go in the same place, there's
not much of a חידוש. chiddush. So מאי לאו, mai lav, so
far for בכור, bechor, presumably the חידוש chiddush here is that you're
dealing with because we're going to assume we're dealing with like stuff
that maybe is roughly the same, all belongs at the bottom part
of the altar, but nevertheless there's got to be some חידוש chiddush
of the פסוק. pasuk. So the חידוש chiddush is you've already done
the application of the עולה olah blood, now you have the שריים
shrayim of the עולה, olah, okay, and the שריים shrayim of the
עולה olah gets mixed up with the בכור. bechor. And the חידוש
chiddush is is that you can put them all at, you can
throw it at the side of the altar. So this seems to
be the proof that the wall counts as the place for שריים,
shrayim, that's what the פסוק pasuk is telling you. ושמע מינה מקום
עולה מקום שריים, U'shma mina mekom olah mekom shrayim,
isn't that what this would tell you? So the גמרא Gemara says
לא, lo, no, תחלת עולה ובכור, techilas olah u'bechor, no, it's the
initial blood of the עולה olah and the initial blood of a
בכור. bechor. So then there is a bigger חידוש chiddush because בכור
bechor gets put once and an עולה olah gets put in two
places. Okay, ומאי קמשמע לן, u'mai kamashma lan, so what's the חידוש?
chiddush? דאין עולין מבטלין זה את זה, de'ein olin m'vatlin zeh es
zeh, that,
now this is Michael asked this question, right, when רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says אין דם מבטל דם, ein dam m'vatel dam, or he
sort of asked it, when the bloods get mixed up it doesn't
even matter, even a tiny quantity never goes out of existence. There's
two unique features of his scenario. One is that it's מין במינו,
min b'mino, blood and blood. The other is is that it's קרבנות,
korbanos, עולים, olim, things that go on the altar. Which one of
those is significant to say that ביטול bitul does not take effect?
So you could say you need both. But the גמרא Gemara makes
it clear that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not limit his הלכה
halacha to cases of קרבנות. korbanos. Remember if we applied it before
to cases of I don't know, urine of a זב zav and
other types of cases, anyway, certainly he applies it to כשרות kashrus
cases. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says מין במינו לא בטל, min b'mino
lo batel, even in cases of כשרות. kashrus. You've got a drop
of טריף treif chicken soup because the chicken wasn't slaughtered correctly fallen
into a vat of a million gallons of כשר kosher chicken soup,
for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you'd have to spill it all out.
Okay, מין במינו לא בטל. min b'mino lo batel. The חכמים Chachamim
agree that blood and blood in some cases isn't בטל. batel. They
learn this from actually the case of what do you call it,
of like we're going to see in a minute when it speaks
about mixing the bloods on יום כיפור Yom Kippur with the blood
of the ox and the blood of the goat. So obviously there's
a lot more blood of ox than blood of a goat and
it's still considered like both bloods are there. But their principle is
אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin m'vatlin zeh es zeh.
Things that go on the altar that get mixed up, it doesn't
go out of existence. So that should make you wonder and go
back about why do we have all those ביטול bitul problems before?
Why do we have to say look at it as if it's
water, look at this, look at that? So it might have been
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it might also have been that
some of those things were not עולין. olin. If some of the
stuff it got mixed up with was the blood of a בעל
מום ba'al mum or the blood of a or the blood of
חולין chulin or wine, those are not עולין. olin. But when it
gets mixed up like עולה olah with
חטאת chatas and those types of bloods, the חכמים Chachamim would agree
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda there's no ביטול, bitul, not because it's
מין במינו, min b'mino, but it's אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה.
ein olin m'vatlin zeh es zeh. Okay, so that's what the חכמים
Chachamim say. So that's and that's pretty much limited to the world
of קדשים. kodshim. So now what we're saying is the חידוש chiddush
of קודש הם, kodesh hem, that if the bloods get mixed up
you could put it on the altar, the חידוש chiddush doesn't have
to be whether this is considered a place for the spilling the
שריים shrayim or not. We could be talking about בכור bechor blood
getting mixed up with עולה olah blood and the חידוש chiddush is
that it's always considered to be present. It doesn't matter which blood
is the majority, whether it's a thousand times more of one than
the other. The חידוש chiddush is that the bloods are always present.
אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin m'vatlin zeh es zeh.
When when things that go on the altar get mixed up, there
is no laws of ביטול. bitul. Now before we go on I
want to say two things about the point about
מקום. makom. Number one, תוספות Tosafot asks a very reasonable question. תוספות
Tosafot says what do you mean that מקום דם makom dam is
מקום makom that the מקום makom of the עולה olah is מקום
שיירים? makom sheyrayim? Just talk about where is it on the altar.
Like if this גמרא gemara here, right, were the- were the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, right? And this were the ramp. Okay. So does anybody remember
where you- and this is the- here's the אהל מועד. ohel moed.
Where do you spill
the blood? You basically spill the blood like here. Okay. I mean
it's one place at least where we spill the blood, which is
the south and the west, or whatever, it's when you directly come
down off of the ramp and so on. Where do you do
the- what do you call it? The- the throwing of the blood?
You do here and here. But this is the first place you
do the spilling of the blood. So תוספות Tosafot has a problem.
תוספות Tosafot says if you're coming to do the עולה olah and
you do the spilling of the blood here, that's not the proper
place for the base. Not because it's on the wall and not
on the base, but because the proper place is this base, not
that base. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot has two answers. One answer basically
is, I mean he has three. One is we're talking about the
second spilling of- the second throwing of blood, but that's not פשט.
pshat. Assuming we're talking about the first throwing of blood, he has
two answers. One is, well, maybe since the verse doesn't explicitly say
which base, even though we learn out that because when you come
down it's got to be near where you are or it's got
to be near the- or whatever, maybe there's some sort of allowance
that even on a different place on the base it still works.
The other answer is that one of the reasons you do it
on this base is it's the first place when you get down
off of the ramp. But תוספות Tosafot says that's only if you
turn right. If you get off the ramp and you turn left,
then this doesn't have a base, so this actually is the first
place. So תוספות Tosafot actually says if you did let's say the
חטאת chatat blood up here and you came down the ramp and
you knew it got mixed- it had עולה olah blood mixed up
with it and you got to- and you've got to do it,
just turn right and this would be an acceptable place for the
base. But he does ask let's not also forget the question about
where on the altar it would be done. Okay that's- what?
Turn left. Turn left, I'm sorry. I was doing it from my
perspective. Turn left. Now, the other question תוספות Tosafot says is when
the גמרא gemara says what's the חידוש chiddush if the בכור bechor
blood gets mixed up with the עולה olah blood, if the חידוש
chiddush isn't that the wall counts as a base, what's the חידוש?
chiddush? And the גמרא gemara says the חידוש chiddush is that it's
not בטל. batel. Blood and blood isn't בטל batel or עולין olin
is not בטל. batel. Look at this little תוספות, Tosafot, because the
גמרא gemara says because there's a bigger חידוש, chiddush, it's blood of
two corners getting mixed up with blood of one- of one wall,
right? תוספות Tosafot says תימה טובא קא משמע לן דאיקרבו למר כדאית
ליה מתנה שתים שהן ארבע ולמר מתנה אחת אף על גב דעבר
על בל תגרע ובל תוסיף. teima tuva ka mashma lan de'ikrebu lemar
kide'it leih matana shtayim shehen arba ulemar matana achat af al gav
de'avar al bal tigra uval tosif. What does- what do you mean
there's no חידוש? chiddush? The whole חידוש chiddush is two get mixed
up with one like Michael sort of said the other day. Michael
said well what do you mean you have to choose between בל
תגרע bal tigra and בל תוסיף, bal tosif, just spill it out.
Okay? So the חידוש chiddush here might be telling you don't spill
it out. If they get mixed up, you're allowed to do it.
Either do two even though it's extra for one of them or
do one even though it's less for the other and might run
afoul of בל תגרע bal tigra and בל תוסיף. bal tosif. The
פסוק pasuk still tells you make a choice but still do it.
Okay? So that's a pretty big חידוש, chiddush, right? So that's a
really good question. So תוספות Tosafot says ושמא יש לומר דכיון דיהיב
לשם מים לית כאן בל תוסיף וגם לא משום בל תגרע כיון
דשב ואל תעשה. veshema yesh lomar dekivan deyahiv leshem mayim leit kan
bal tosif vegam lo mishum bal tigra kivan deshev ve'al ta'aseh. תוספות
Tosafot says okay but somehow we would have figured that out ourselves.
You didn't need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that. Okay? Because
I could have said you know you pretend the extra blood is
water, whatever. But that's not- you know- but the question is much
better than the answer, right? If you get it mixed up and
you have to choose between do I do two applications which is
extra- or two which is four which is extra or one which
is fewer and it's a type of בל תגרע bal tigra or
בל תוסיף, bal tosif, logically I could have said don't do any
and spill it all out. So תוספות Tosafot says let's say that's
what the פסוק pasuk is telling you, that if the bloods get
mixed up you still have to find a way to apply it.
All right. Anyway the גמרא gemara doesn't say that. Okay? So the
גמרא gemara says so don't we learn from קודש הם kodesh hem
that if the bloods get mixed up that the place of where
you put the blood of the עולה olah is considered an acceptable
place for שיירים? sheyrayim? And the גמרא's gemara's answer is no. I
mean תוספות, Tosafot, excuse me. The גמרא's gemara's answer is no, that
maybe what the פסוק pasuk teaches you is that blood is not-
is that the bloods don't- aren't מבטל mevatel one another because אין
עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin mevatlin zeh et zeh. ומהי
קא משמע לן דאין עולין מבטלין זה את זה umai ka mashma
lan de'ein olin mevatlin zeh et zeh that even if it's the
beginning of the bloods of both an עולה olah and a בכור
bechor they- there's no ביטול. bitul. So
the גמרא gemara says הי ומהי מולקח מדם הפר ומדם השעיר נפקא.
hai umai milukach midam hapar umidam hase'ir nafka. We learn it by
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It says you take from the blood of
the- of the ox and the blood of the goat and presumably
you mix them together and you put them on the מזבח mizbe'ach
and it's still considered like both bloods are present even though there's
a lot more blood of an ox. So that teaches you that
אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin mevatlin zeh et zeh.
So the גמרא gemara says תנאי היא. tannai hi. It's a debate
of תנאים. tannaim. What's the source of this הלכה halacha that things
that go on the altar don't cause ביטול bitul with one another?
איכא דנפקא ליה מהכא ואיכא דנפקא ליה מהכא. ika denafka leih mehacha
ve'ika denafka leih mehacha. Some learn it from the blood of the
ox and the goat and some learn it from this case of
קודש הם kodesh hem and we're going to say when we turn
the דף daf why you would learn it from one פסוק, pasuk,
why you prefer one פסוק pasuk over another. Okay. So now the
גמרא gemara continues. מתיב רבא. metiv Rava. So רבא Rava asks, again
this question about whether תחילת עולה- techilat olah whether the place of
the עולה olah is מקום שיירים makom sheyrayim or not. והקריבו בני
אהרן את הדם וזרקו את הדם על המזבח סביב. vehikrivu bnei aharon
et hadam vezarku et hadam al hamizbe'ach saviv. They should
throw the
blood. Okay, יכל yachol אין ein לי li אלא ela אלו eilu
שנתערבו shenisravu בתמורתה bisimurasah שהרי sheharei מחיים mechayim תיקרב. tikarev. So it's
telling you that if certain animals get mixed up, you bring the
blood regardless. Somehow the words דם dam דם dam says you always
bring the blood even if things get mixed up. So the first
sort of assumption I'll have that you can bring it if it
gets mixed up, and this is partly missing from our quote. רש"י
Rashi fills in the line based on the ספרא Sifra whatever, that
it says that let's say
a, let's say the earlier cases in the משנה, mishnah, the blood
of a קרבן korban gets mixed up with the blood of חולין,
chullin, or the blood of an עולה olah gets mixed up with
an עולה, olah, or the blood of an עולה olah gets mixed
up with a תמורה. tmurah. In all those cases you can bring
it, you throw the blood. Why? אין ein לי li אלא ela
אלו eilu שנתערבו shenisravu בתמורתה bisimurasah שהרי sheharei מחיים mechayim תיקרב, tikarev,
because even if they had gotten mixed up when the animals were
alive, you would say slaughter them. If an עולה olah gets mixed
up with a חולין, chullin, a non-sanctified animal, stretch your memory back,
remember we had that in an earlier משנה. mishnah. The הלכה halacha
was you can just go ahead and sanctify that חולין chullin if
it's a תמים tamim and then bring both of them, right? Or
if an עולה olah gets mixed up with an עולה, olah, slaughter
them all and just bring all the blood. Or we didn't discuss
תמורה, tmurah, but if an עולה olah gets mixed up with a
תמורה tmurah with its replacement. So in those cases, even if the
animals were alive we wouldn't hesitate to tell you slaughter it and
throw all the blood. So of course all the blood can be
put once the blood gets mixed up. It's all essentially the same
blood anyway. Okay, so מנין minayin לרבות lerabbos תודה todah ושלמים? ushlamim?
How do you know that if an עולה olah blood gets mixed
up with תודה todah and שלמים ushlamim blood that you would go
ahead and throw it? Because if it was an עולה olah קרבן
korban that got mixed up with a תודה todah or שלמים, ushlamim,
you would
actually, you wouldn't necessarily slaughter it לכתחילה. lechatchilah. You might let it
graze and redeem the value, etc. Okay, right? Is that what the
משנה mishnah says? Does anybody remember that from this משנה, mishnah, what
happens when תודה todah gets mixed up? I forgot actually. Let's go
way back to what happens when that happens.
Okay, anyway, ע"א ע"ב. ayin aleph amud beis. Let's take a look.
קדשים kadashim בקדשים bekadashim מין min במינו, bimino, קדשים kadashim בקדשים bekadashim
מין min בשאינו beshe'eino מינו, mino, ירעו. yiru. You let them graze.
Okay, even though, right? So,
oh, and the reason is, right, I was trying to remember why,
because the blood is exactly the same. So the reason is if
an עולה olah gets mixed up with a שלמים ushlamim you have
to let it graze and redeem it and buy new קרבנות korbanos
is because of what you're going to do with the meat. What
you're going to do with the meat is different. Okay, so maybe
if an עולה olah gets mixed up with a שלמים, ushlamim, an
עולה olah blood and a שלמים ushlamim blood, since if they were
alive you wouldn't slaughter them both, you'd wait for them to get
a blemish, maybe now that the blood's get mixed up maybe you
don't throw both of the bloods. So מנין minayin לרבות lerabbos תודה
todah ושלמים? ushlamim? מרבה marbeh תודה todah ושלמים. ushlamim. No, that's also
what I would have, I knew that you would have done it
from maybe one of the words דם. dam. שבאים sheba'im בנדבה bindavah
ונדר. vineder. At least they're similar that they're free will sacrifices, כמוה,
kamoah, like an עולה. olah. מנין minayin לרבות lerabbos אשם? asham? How
do I know to include even an אשם, asham,
which is an obligation? מרבה marbeh את es האשם ha'asham שטעון sheta'un
מתן matan ארבע arba כמוה. kamoah. Because at least an אשם asham
it's put on the מזבח mizbe'ach just like עולה olah blood. So
if an אשם asham blood and עולה olah blood get mixed up,
even though they're fundamentally different sacrifices, I would have known that you
put them both on the מזבח mizbe'ach because essentially you put them
all at the same place. בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, פסח pesach מנין?
minayin? How do I know if עולה olah blood gets mixed up
with בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח, pesach, which one of them
you put four applications or two that are four, the other you
just put one application? How do I know you still throw the
blood? תלמוד talmud לומר lomar דם dam דם. dam. So the replication
of דם dam says even in those cases you apply the blood.
So pretty much just like we said before, before we made the
same point from קודש הם, kodesh heim, here we make the point
from דם dam דם, dam, even if different sacrifices of different bloods
get mixed up, you put it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So the
גמרא gemara repeats what it says before: מאי mai לאו lav סוף
sof עולה olah ובכור? uvchor? Isn't the חידוש chiddush that even if
it's the remainder of the עולה olah blood, the שיריים shiyrayim getting
mixed up with the בכור, bechor, you can still apply
it? ושמע מינה מקום עולה מקום שיריים. v'shema mina makom Olah makom
Shiyaryim. You see that throwing it on the wall, which is what
you would do with it as בכור bechor blood, counts for the
application of the שיריים shiyrayim. of the עולה. olah Or else what's
the חידוש? chiddush? So the גמרא gemara says: לא, lo, תחילת techilas
עולה olah. ובכור, uvchor, which is of course פשטא peshata of the
ברייתא. braisa. It's so funny that the ברייתא, beraita the גמרא gemara
assumes in its argument we're talking about the remainder of the blood.
There's no hint that we're talking about the remainder of the blood.
It says no, we're talking about the initial blood of the עולה
olah getting mixed up with the בכור. bechor. ומאי umai קמשמע kamashma
לן? lan? What's the חידוש? chiddush? So again what you want to
say is what תוספות tosafos says. What you want to say is
that the חידוש chiddush is that even though the עולה olah blood
is four and the בכור bechor blood is one, you're still allowed
to do it. Either you do extra or you do fewer, you
know, that's the debate of בל bal תוסיף, tosif, בל bal תגרע,
tigra, but you still go ahead and do it. But again the
גמרא Gemara somehow completely ignoring that and saying no, the חידוש chiddush
of עולה olah blood and בכור bechor blood if it's not about
the שיריים, shiyrayim you know what the חידוש chiddush is? דאין de'ein
אלו eilu מבטלין mevatlin זה zeh את es זה. zeh. Okay the
חידוש chiddush is like we said before that even though it's blood
and blood and there's a minority of one and a majority of
the other. other, it does, the minority does not go away because
it's all stuff that goes on the altar. So that's the חידוש
chiddush *chidush*. It's not a חידוש chiddush *chidush* about שיריים shiyrayim, *shirayim*,
we're not talking about the שיריים Shiyaryim. *shirayim*. It's not a חידוש
*chidush* of four getting mixed up with one, somehow we don't need
a פסוק *pasuk* to tell me that, and the חידוש *chidush* is
just that there's no ביטול *bitul*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
what do you mean, we know that from somewhere else? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הא ומאי קמשמע לן ביטול זה את זה
*ha umai kamashma lan bitul zeh et zeh*? ולקח מדם הפר ומדם
השעיר נפקא *v'lakach midam hapar uvidam hase'ir nafka*, wait a minute, we
learned that from the blood of the ox and the blood of
the goat on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* that the blood
of the goat doesn't go out of existence.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, תנאי היא *tnai hi*, it's a
debate of תנאים *tannaim*. איכא דנפקא ליה מהכא ואיכא דנפקא ליה מהכא
*ika de'nafka lei me'hacha v'ika de'nafka lei me'hacha*. So now we have
some learn it from one, some learn it from, so we have
three possible פסוקים *psukim* to tell me אין עולין מבטלין זה את
זה *ein olin mevatlin zeh et zeh*.
One is blood of the ox and blood of the goat, one
is קודש הם *kodesh hem* by the word by בכור *bechor*, זה
*zeh* the bloods are all still present. And the other is דם
דם *dam dam*. Okay, so why
what's the problem the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say with each
פסוק *pasuk*, like why wasn't there a consensus that one just pick
one of those פסוקים *psukim*?
Well, because יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom
Kippur*'s its own thing maybe. All right, so let's take a look.
So that's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והני תנאים מולקח מדם הפר ומדם השעיר לא
ילפי
*v'hani tannaim mivlakach midam hapar uvidam hase'ir lo yalpi*, why didn't they
learn from the ox and the goat? Now not like Michael said,
that it's יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*'s different, but קסברי אין מערבין לקרנות
*kasavri ein me'arvin lekranot*. They say because you're assuming that you mix
the bloods together, and the חידוש *chidush* was that they were both
still present. But there's an opinion in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
you don't mix the bloods together. That actually you apply the blood,
although we say that in our עבודה *avoda* יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
that they mix the bloods anyway, that's a debate. There are some
that say you apply the blood of the ox and the blood
of the goat separately on the מזבח הזהב *mizbeiach hazahav*. So if
you apply them separately and you never mixed it together, then of
course there's no proof from this case because you don't even have
the scenario where the bloods are mixed together. מדם דם לא ילפי
*midam dam lo yalpi*, now why not learn out from דם דם
*dam dam*? דם דם לא משמע להו *dam dam lo mashma lehu*,
yeah, just the repetition of the word דם *dam* it's not such
an extra word, it's you know the תורה *Torah* says you throw
the blood on the altar, to say that that extra word דם
*dam* is to tell you that you know even if the bloods
are mixed together it's okay, that's not such an extra word. אלא
מקודש הם מאי טעמא לא ילפי *ella mikodesh hem mai ta'ama lo
yalpi*, but why didn't they learn from קודש הם *kodesh hem*? That's
in the plural, that seems like an extra phrase. So that should
have been a phrase we all could have agreed on is telling
you that even if the bloods get mixed together. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says no, קסברי קודש הם לא ילפי *kasavri kodesh hem lo
yalpi*, because they learn something else from קודש הם *kodesh hem*. קודש
הם *kodesh hem*, they are holy, הם קרבים ואין תמורתם קריבה *hem
krevim v'ein tmuratam kreva* to tell you that by a בכור *bechor*,
right, since a בכור *bechor* is not done through your verbal sanctifying
of it, a בכור *bechor* is just a בכור *bechor* by virtue
of it being born a בכור *bechor*. So therefore if you make
something a תמורה *tmura*, it can't be brought.
The general rule is specifically by a בכור *bechor*, or from the
other ones? The other ones you did sanctify.
Right, so by בכור *bechor*, specifically by בכור *bechor*. Other things you
would bring a תמורה *tmura*, but specifically by a בכור *bechor* the
הלכה halacha *halacha* is that the תמורה *tmura* of a בכור *bechor*
cannot be brought as a sacrifice. It's sanctified, has to be you
would have to have it, but it can't be brought as a
sacrifice. הם קרבים ואין תמורתם קריבה *hem krevim v'ein tmuratam kreva*. So
that's what you learn קודש הם *kodesh hem*, they, only the בכורים
*bechorim* themselves. Has nothing to do with the blood. ואידך *v'idach*, now
if you learn from קודש הם *kodesh hem* the bloods being mixed
together, where do you learn this הלכה halacha *halacha*? נפקא ליה משור
אם שה להשם הוא *nafka lei mishor im seh lashem hu*. You
know, whether whatever the firstborn is, whether it's an ox or a
sheep it is to God. הוא קרב *hu karev* it is to
God, ואין תמורתם קריבה *v'ein tmuratam kreva*.
So therefore קודש הם *kodesh hem* can't teach you that,
so קודש הם *kodesh hem* then therefore is free to teach you
about the bloods. Okay, fine. So therefore we learned these different issues,
we have not resolved this question about whether the side of the
altar is a place for the שיריים Shiyaryim. *shirayim*. We've we've learned
is a couple of different פסוקים *psukim* that speak about bloods getting
mixed together and might be teaching you that הלכה halacha *halacha*, תוספות
*Tosafot* wants to know why aren't they teaching you the הלכה *halacha*
that even though one is four and one is one, you're allowed
to make a choice and either do too many or too few?
And what the גמרא *Gemara* says is it's also teaching you the
הלכה *halacha* of אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה *ein olin mevatlin
zeh et zeh*. All right, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says, תא
שמע *tasha*. נתן למעלה ולא נמלך *natan lemala v'lo nimlach*. Now we're
not done, we're still going to try to prove, and this really
was the case that it seemed like he explained before, that actually
yes, the remnant of the חטאת Chatas *chatas* blood that's put on
the walls counts as the spilling of the שיריים Shiyaryim *shirayim*. Why?
Because what does the ברייתא braisa *braita* say? The ברייתא braisa *braita*
says the following. נתן למעלה ולא נמלך *natan lemala v'lo nimlach*. The
the blood of the חטאת Chatas *chatas* and עולה olah *olah* got
mixed up together, the כהן *kohen* went, he didn't ask permission, he
applied some of it at the top of the altar. So then
it says, אלו ואלו מודים שיחזור ויתן למטה *elu v'eilu modim she'yachzor
v'yitein lemata*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer וחכמים *Rabbi Eliezer v'Chachamim*, even though
the חכמים Chachomim *Chachamim* normally say I won't let you put it
in the wrong place, here they'll say I will let you put
this after the חטאת Chatas *chatas* blood was already placed, I'll let
you put the mixture below. So if you're putting the mixture below,
presumably that's exactly our point. You're putting it in the on the
wall to throw on the wall like an עולה Olah. *olah* blood
and presumably that's counting for the שיריים Shiyaryim. *shirayim* of the חטאת
Chatas *chatas*. So this is an explicit seems to be explicit evidence
that they agree that the wall. that you're using for the עולה
Olah blood counts for the spilling of the
שיריים. Shiyaryim אלו ואלו מודים שיחזיר ויתן למטה. Eilu v'eilu modim sheyachzir
v'yiten lematah. Go ahead and put it below. So the גמרא אלו
ואלו
עולין לו eilu v'eilu olin lo and both count. It counts both
for חטאת Chatas and for an עולה. Olah Okay, מאי לאו דעירב
חטאת ועולה? Mai lav de'eirev Chatas v'Olah? It sounds like חטאת Chatas
and עולה Olah blood got mixed up together. וכיון דיהב ליה למעלה
v'keivan deyahav lei l'ma'ala and since you put the חטאת Chatas blood
above, הוי ליה שיריים. hava lei hu Shiyaryim. Now you have remnant
of חטאת Chatas blood mixed up with עולה Olah blood and it's
saying put it on the wall. So וקתני אלו ואלו מודים שיחזיר
ויתן למטה, v'ketani eilu v'eilu modim sheyachzir v'yiten lematah, put it below.
So it seems like a pretty darn good proof because now the
חכמים chachamim allow you to do it that this is considered an
acceptable place for the spilling of the שיריים. Shiyaryim You have remnant
of חטאת Chatas blood mixed with עולה Olah and it says go
ahead and put it on the wall. Okay, so ושמע ushma מינה
minah מקום makom עולה Olah מקום makom שיריים. Shiyaryim. That seems like
a pretty darn good proof. Okay.
So the גמרא as is its want, basically even after you've given
a really good proof, says you know there is a way to
get out of it. Let's see what the way to get out
of it is. Okay. So the גמרא says like this. כי אתא
רב יצחק בר יוסף, Ki ata Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef, when רב
יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and remember,
one of the אמוראים Amora'im who disagree with this הלכה and say
that you cannot use the wall for שיריים Shiyaryim is רב יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So anyway, although I don't
know if רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is the same time, anyway, so
it doesn't matter, anyway רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak came from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אמר אמרי במערבא, amar, amri b'ma'arava, here's what they say
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to get out of this proof even
though it does sound like yes, the remnant of the חטאת Chatas
blood can go on the wall and it works.
הכי אמרי במערבא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דעירב חטאת חיצונה בשיריים. Hachi
amri b'ma'arava, hacha b'mai askinan, kegon de'irev Chatas chitzona b'Shiyaryim. Okay, so
what happened was is through actually, it's two different types of חטאות
Chatases blood got mixed up. Not חטאת Chatas and עולה olah blood.
You basically used had an inner חטאת Chatas which you put on
the inner altar and you have the remnant of that blood, and
the remnant of that blood gets spilled at the base of the
outer altar and that gets mixed up with חטאת Chatas blood. Okay.
So that, and then the question is what do you do? So
you can't put it at the top because that's the wrong place
for the blood that's already the שיריים. Shiyaryim So that's why we
would say don't do anything. But if you went ahead and you
actually did put it at the top, now what do you have
left in the mixture? שיריים Shiyaryim and שיריים Shiyaryim blood. So then
you spill it at the base. So when it says if you
already put it, go ahead and finish it up, that's not finish
it up and put it on the wall and it counts as
עולה olah, and שיריים. Shiyaryim No, now you have שיריים Shiyaryim of
the outer חטאת Chatas? and שיריים Shiyaryim of the inner חטאת Chatas
and now just spill it at the base. Okay. So the גמרא
אלו ואלו מודים שיחזיר ויתן למטה. eilu v'eilu modim sheyachzir v'yiten lematah.
So the גמרא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דעירב חטאת חיצונה בשיריים. hacha
b'mai askinan, kegon de'irev Chatas chitzona b'Shiyaryim. אמר ליה אביי Amar lei
Abaye and ונימא מר כגון דעירב בשיריים דשיריים. v'neima mar kegon de'irev
b'Shiyaryim d'Shiyaryim.
So therefore and that's what it is. But if it were עולה
olah blood it wouldn't work. But it's because it's שיריים Shiyaryim and
שיריים Shiyaryim you spill it at the base. But לכתחילה l'chatchila don't
do it because it starts by being שיריים Shiyaryim and חטאת Chatas?
and don't therefore put חטאת Chatas at the top of the altar.
אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye ונימא מר כגון דעירב בשיריים דשיריים.
v'neima mar kegon de'irev b'Shiyaryim d'Shiyaryim. Why do you have to say
that it was mixed with the שיריים Shiyaryim of the inner חטאת?
Chatas. Why not, as long as you're reinterpreting this, why not just
say שיריים Shiyaryim of an outer חטאת Chatas got mixed up with
the beginning of the blood of an outer חטאת? Chatas, Okay. דילמא
הא קמשמע לן אפילו מאן דאמר שיריים מעכבין חסורי אין מעכבין. Dilma
ha kamashma lan afilu man d'amar Shiyaryim me'akvin, chasrei ein me'akvin.
Maybe what you're trying to teach us is you could have given
that scenario, but what you're trying to teach us is there's a
position that the spilling of the שיריים Shiyaryim of an inner חטאת
Chatas
is necessary to make it valid. Normally the spilling of the שיריים
Shiyaryim is never necessary to make something valid. The one possible exception
is of an inner חטאת. Chatas Okay.
And by the way, and that might be why we gave that
scenario. Because if we had been talking about the שיריים Shiyaryim of
an outer חטאת Chatas. got mixed up with a חטאת, Chatas remember
the end of the ברייתא braisa teaches oh if you already did
it above just do it below and they both work and they
both count. Well if all that's left is שיריים Shiyaryim. and שיריים
Shiyaryim blood, of course they both count even if you didn't spill
it at all, right? The שיריים Shiyaryim, in the end doesn't prevent
the קרבן korban from being good. But if we're talking about in
this scenario an inner חטאת Chatas that was right, so there you
might need the שיריים Shiyaryim to be spilled in order to count.
So that's why we're giving the scenario that you've got the שיריים
Shiyaryim of an inner חטאת Chatas being mixed up with the blood
of an outer חטאת. Chatas And therefore it's a real issue because
the inner חטאת Chatas you might not be done yet. It might
you might not be יוצא yotzei until you spill the שיריים. Shiyaryim
And therefore we're saying if you did the top חטאת chatas, and
now you got שיריים Shiyaryim, and שיריים, Shiyaryim now spill it all
out at the base. And that validates the inner חטאת chatas, because
it's also because it's being spilled at the base. Okay. And רבא
Rava says and maybe part of the חידוש here is also
that even though some of the שיריים shirayim. of the inner חטאת
chatas, now got put at the top of the altar, don't say
that that prevents the spilling of the שיריים shirayim from counting. Even
if you need the spilling of the שיריים shirayim, of the inner
חטאת chatas to validate it, it's not כשר kosher until that happens,
even if you had only שירי שיריים shirei Shiyaryim as it were,
you know the remnant not the whole שיריים, shirayim some of the
שיריים shirayim. that also counts. So maybe you're creating this scenario: A,
to tell a חידוש that that's a case where you need the
spilling in order to validate, and B, that even though some was
already used, it's still valid. Okay, but the bottom line is, if
this discussion is where it says just spill it at the bottom
and you're יוצא yotzei and both count, it's talking about an עולה
olah and a חטאת, chatas then you're right, that proves our point
that the side of the wall counts for the spilling of שיריים.
shirayim And that's why the rabbis would allow it. But the גמרא
is saying you're not forced to read the ברייתא braisa, that way.
The ברייתא braisa could be talking about שיריים shirayim. and a חטאת,
chatas and therefore it's just telling you, and therefore it's telling you
if you already did the חטאת, chatas, now just spill the שיריים,
shirayim, you have שיריים shirayim. and שיריים. shirayim. And maybe it's not
telling you anything that the wall counts like שיריים shirayim is good
for שיריים. shirayim. Okay, so now so we haven't concluded that question
whether the wall is a good place for the spilling of the
שיריים, but again the simple case of the ברייתא seemed to indicate
that. Okay, now we just end this discussion with the following line,
tying us back into yesterday. אמר
ליה רב תוספאה לרבינא, Amar lei Rav Tosfaa leRavina, so רב תוספאה
Rav Tosfaa said to רבינא: Ravina: הוקימנא היא ברוב עליונים וקאי ללמעלה
שיר תחתונים ועוד. Hokimna hi berov elyonim vekaye lelamala shir tachtonim veod.
He says: Wait a minute, you're trying to say spill it at
the base should be a proof or spill, sorry, take the blood,
put it on the wall should be a proof that the עולה,
olah the wall counts for the spilling of שיריים. But if you
remember yesterday, he said we said that you know it was six
units of חטאת chatas. blood, four units of עולה olah, blood, you
did four and a little bit at the top, the whole everything
we said yesterday, and basically we said that the case wasn't that
you were making the עולה olah good, right? The case was that
you were just making the חטאת chatas good, that it said if
you already did it at the top, just go ahead and finish
the bottom and spill it out at the base at the bottom
and you were making the חטאת chatas good, and that you weren't
making the
עולה olah good. So why do you think this whole discussion is
relevant? So he said, אמר ליה הני מילי למאן דאמר למאן דאמרינן
מעיקרא אין בילה. Amar lei hani mili leman deamar leman deamrinan meikara
ein bila. That was when we were thinking to say that you
can't assume
total mixture, total dispersion, and we had to give a very forced
read of this ברייתא, right? In the forced read of the ברייתא
was, you know, there's four units of עולה, olah six of חטאת,
chatas you put on the top four and a little bit etc.
and the only thing that's good is the חטאת. chatas So that
was a very forced read, and according to that forced read, fine,
it wouldn't be a proof for our discussion either. But that wasn't
the simple read of it. Okay, מסקנא בכוסות פליגי, Maskana bekosos pligi,
in the end we said that even if you wanted to say
אין בילה, ein bila, the way of explaining those cases was not
that the bloods got mixed up, you know, but was that the
various bowls got mixed up. Okay, and once we're saying that, we
could say both the עולה olah is good and the חטאת chatas
is good, either because the blood is equally mixed and you're throwing
them both, or because
the cups are mixed and you're throwing from each cup, so you
know you're getting everything onto the altar. So at the end of
the day we did not stick with that answer, and therefore we
still have our question: If we're saying both the חטאת chatat, and
the עולה olah are good, if you did it at the top,
just finish at the bottom, then that would seem to be finish
at the bottom and throw it on the wall and that counts.
If the חכמים Chachamim let you do this לכתחילה, lechatchila, that counts
for the spilling of the שיריים. So that proves that the wall
counts. And in the end we said, okay, assuming it's חטאת chatas,
and עולה blood, you're right, but maybe it's חטאת chatas and שיריים
blood and we're talking not about throwing it at the wall, but
spilling it on the base. Okay, so in the end we do
not resolve whether or not this counts, the wall counts as a
place for spilling of the שיריים.
When they're accepting the throwing on the wall, are they considering that
the blood's going to go down to the base?
Yes, that's why the reason they are, I should have said that,
the reason throwing at the top wall wouldn't work, A because it's
top and you know the altar's generally divided top and bottom, so
a base is a bottom thing, not a top thing, but also
because the top of the top doesn't run down to the base,
it hits a ledge. Although you could throw it at the top
half under the ledge, right? Because there's an אמה amah between the
top half and the ledge. But the basic assumption here is that
yes, since there's nothing impeding the blood, you know, from the wall
to run down to the base. But an interesting question would be:
Let's say there was a minimum amount and it stuck on the
wall and it didn't run down. You know, now you could say,
I don't know, gravity it'll eventually run down, but I don't know
what you did, like before it had a chance to run down
you wiped it off the side. You know, is it because it
runs down or is it just no, since it's right, you know,
the base is right below it and in theory it could run
down and the base is right there, that
counts. That seems to be the point. It doesn't seem like it's
saying it's good once it runs down, but maybe it's because it's
in a scenario that naturally it would run down, that might be
why it's considered to be the base. Okay, so let's keep on
going, let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, הניתנין בפנים שנתערבו
בניתנין בחוץ ישפכו לאמה. Hanitnin bifnim shenisarvu benitnin bachutz yishpechu laamah. Now
blood that goes supposed to be in the inner sanctum, okay, let's
say it's the blood of an inner חטאת chatas like פר העלם
דבר של ציבור, Par He’elam Davar Shel Tzibbur, let's say a יום
כיפור animal, right, that got mixed up with blood that was supposed
to be on the outer altar, okay,
so spill it, spill it out. Now the גמרא's going to ask
that sort of
follows... חכמים Chachamim say when they're different places you have to spill
it out, but why doesn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer just say, put
it on the inner, put it on the outer and each time
it's the wrong one just sort of say we'll look at the
wrong blood as if it's water? So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to
ask that. Now, נתן בחוץ וחזר ונתן בפנים. nasan bachutz v'chazar v'nasan
bifnim. Let's say you didn't ask. You didn't ask permission. Again, the
general rule about these משניות mishnayos is that it's always easier to
ask forgiveness than permission. So you didn't ask permission and you went
ahead and you first threw it on the outer altar, then the
inner altar. So then כשר, kasher, בדיעבד bedieved it's כשר. kasher. You
did it in both places. You shouldn't have done the wrong blood,
but you did it and it's כשר. kasher. Now, בפנים וחזר ונתן
בחוץ. bifnim v'chazar v'nasan bachutz. Let's say you started and you took
the blood inside and you put it on the inner altar, the
incense altar, and then you put it on the outer altar. So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva בחוץ, bachutz, רבי עקיבא פוסל
וחכמים מכשירים. Rabbi Akiva posel v'chachamim machshirim.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's invalid and the חכמים Chachamim say
it's valid. Why? שרבי עקיבא אומר כל דמים שנכנסו לכפר בהיכל פסולים,
sheRabbi Akiva omer kol damim shenichnasu l'chaper baheichal psulim,
because the verse says by a חטאת, chatas it says by a
sin offering, it says וכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד
לכפר בקודש לא תאכל באש תשרף. v'chol chatat asher yuva midama el
ohel mo'ed l'chaper bakodesh lo te'achel ba'esh tisaref.
Any sin offering whose blood is brought to the inner sanctum for
atonement shall not be eaten, it should be burnt. Now, there's three
possible points to be possible ways to read this verse. One is
that there are חטאות chata'os which are supposed to be brought, the
blood on the inner sanctum, right, like on יום כיפור, the goat
and the and the ox, or like the ox by the פר
העלם דבר של ציבור. par he'elem davar shel tzibur. Any animal that
the blood is put in the inner sanctum, and the only animals
that blood ever go into the inner sanctum are חטאות chata'os animals.
So the הלכה of חטאות פנימיות, chata'os pnimiyos, an inner חטאת, chatas?
is that you don't eat the meat, you burn it. So the
simple sense of the verse, any חטאת chatas. that blood goes on
the inside is saying because there's a subset of חטאות chata'os that
this is what you're supposed to do, and for those חטאות chata'os
that this is what you're supposed to do, don't eat the meat,
burn the meat, okay? But the next level of reading that verse
is, let's say you accidentally or intentionally, whatever, it doesn't matter, you
brought an outer חטאת chatas blood and you brought that blood in
the inner sanctum. Well, the verse is saying any חטאת'ס chatas's blood,
even one that belonged on the outside, as soon as you bring
the blood on the inside, you now have made that חטאת chatas
something that cannot be eaten and the meat has to be destroyed.
Well, what about if it's not a חטאת? chatas, What about if
you bring עולה blood on the inside, or שלמים shlamim blood on
the inside? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's all the same,
it's not limited to a חטאת. chatas. So you got your עולה
blood mixed up with your inner חטאת chatas blood. If you go
ahead and you first sprinkle it on the outside and then the
inside, so then it's כשר kasher and you can eat, well let's
say a שלמים shlamim blood, so take a case where you can
eat.
שלמים shlamim blood and inner חטאת chatas blood mixed up. If you
do the outside and then the inside, it's fine. You did the
outside, the שלמים shlamim was good. Now when you're doing the inside,
although you're bringing שלמים shlamim blood on the inside, it says אשר
יובא מדמה לכפר בקודש, asher yuva midama l'chaper bakodesh, you're bringing it
on the inside for the sake of atonement, and here the atonement
of the שלמים shlamim was already done, okay, and the שלמים shlamim
was already a כשר kasher שלמים. shlamim. So you can't invalidate it
once it's כשר, kasher, okay? So in that case, go ahead and
they're both כשר. kasher. But if you started by bringing it on
the inside, the שלמים shlamim status was still not valid yet, the
blood hadn't been thrown and its blood was being brought on the
inside, okay? So there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say, ah, you've
invalidated your שלמים. shlamim. It's not a חטאת, chatas but I don't
think the הלכה is limited to a חטאת. chatas Okay, so רבי
עקיבא פוסל וחכמים מכשירים, Rabbi Akiva posel v'chachamim machshirim, שרבי עקיבא אומר
sheRabbi Akiva omer because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say כל דמים
שנכנסו לכפר בהיכל פסולים, kol damim shenichnasu l'chaper baheichal psulim, any bloods,
whatever the sacrifice is, that are brought inside the היכל, heichal, פסולים,
psulim, the animal becomes invalid if the blood was not already had
had if the sacrifice was not already כשר. kasher. So if you
do this first, it invalidates the שלמים. shlamim. וחכמים אומרים חטאת בלבד,
v'chachamim omrim chatat bilvad, only a חטאת chatas, blood invalidates, does the
חטאת chatas, become invalid if an outer חטאת chatas blood is brought
on the inside. רבי אליעזר אומר אף אשם. Rabbi Eliezer omer af
asham. This gets us back way to the first משנה mishnah of
the מסכת, masechta, remember the first משנה mishnah of the מסכת masechta
when you had a שלא לשמה shelo lishma thought that it invalidated
a חטאת chatas and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said, ah, an אשם
asham is just like a חטאת, right? So here too he says
the only blood that when you bring blood inside it invalidates an
outer sacrifice, true it's a חטאת, but it's also an
אשם, asham, שנאמר כחטאת כאשם. she'ne'emar kechatas ke'asham. So you have three
possibilities. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says any blood, the חכמים Chachamim say
of any outer blood brought inside invalidates, חכמים say just חטאת and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says חטאת and אשם. asham. Okay, so let's
just get a little bit to the עמוד א' amud aleph here.
So the גמרא says let's just first deal with why according to
רבי אליעזר when the bloods get mixed up, right, does he say
spill it, spill it, why why does he not disagree here as
well and say wait, לכתחילה lechatchila go ahead and do it and
pretend that it's water like he was like he's been saying until
now, okay? So why because the whole debate in the משנה mishnah
is that you didn't listen and you went ahead and you did
it. But in the משנה *Mishnah* it basically says you're supposed to
spill it out, for Rabbi Eliezer normally allows you to do it
לכתחילה *lechatchila*. Why didn't he allow you to do it לכתחילה *lechatchila*
in our משנה *Mishnah*? וניפלג נמי רבי אליעזר בהא *veniflag nami Rabbi
Eliezer beha*, let Rabbi Eliezer also disagree on this case. היכי להוי
*heichi lav*, because what should you do? ניתיב בחוץ והדר ניתיב לפנים
*nesiv bachutz vehadar nesiv lifnim*, that would make sense. First do it
on the outer altar, so you don't, so you validate the outer
sacrifice before you bring its blood on the inside, and then go
ahead and do it on the inner one. And when you're doing
it on the outer one, just say, I'm just looking at like
the inner blood as if it's water. Okay. No, you don't have
a right to do that. כשם שמצוה להקדים עליונים לתחתונים כך מצוה
להקדים פנים לחוץ *keshem shemitzva lehaktim elyonim letachtonim kach mitzva lehaktim pnim
lechutz* that you have to do the, the same way you have
to do the top קרבן *korban* before the bottom, you have to
do a חטאת *chatas* before an עולה *olah*. Remember in and in
all our scenarios before it said, you first did the חטאת *chatas*,
you, if this mixture, you first did it at the top and
then at the bottom. So the same way חטאת *chatas* comes before
עולה *olah*, inner sacrifices come before outer ones. So if you've got
this mixture, Rabbi Eliezer would say, even if I'm prepared to look
at it like water, I would insist that you first do, you
bring in on the inside first before you do the outside. And
then if, and so okay, so why not do that? So then
the answer is obvious. וניתיב לפנים והדר ניתיב לחוץ *venesiv lifnim vehadar
nesiv lechutz*, so why not then go ahead and take the mixture
first on the inside and then the outside? כיון דאיכא חטאת ואשם
*keivan deika chatas veasham*, so he says like this: he might because
we know Rabbi Eliezer does not agree with Rabbi Akiva, right? Rabbi
Eliezer is at the end of the משנה *Mishnah*. He says if
it's a שלמים *shelamim*, if it's an עולה *olah*, you won't invalidate.
So why doesn't he say when an עולה *olah* blood gets mixed
up with an inner חטאת *chatas* blood, bring it on the inside
first? And he says that that doesn't invalidate. The only thing that
gets invalidated is חטאת *chatas* and אשם *asham* blood that's brought on
the inside, right? So at least if it's a mixture, I get
if it's a mixture of an outer חטאת *chatas* and an inner
חטאת *chatas*, you can't do it on the outside first because you
always have to go inside first. You go on the inside, you've
invalidated it because you had the blood of a חטאת *chatas* or
the blood of an אשם *asham*. And he says blood of an
אשם *asham* also gets invalidated. But if it's עולה *olah* and שלמים
*shelamim* blood that gets mixed up with inner חטאת *chatas*, bring it
on the inside first, it won't invalidate the עולה *olah* and שלמים
*shelamim*. He doesn't hold like Rabbi Akiva. And then go ahead and
bring it on the outer one. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, yes,
in theory you could do that. אבל כיון דאיכא חטאת ואשם דכי
נכנס דמם פסולים *keivan deika chatas veasham dechi nichnas damam psulim*, since
there are some scenarios where it would invalidate, if it wasn't עולה
*olah* and שלמים *shelamim* blood that got mixed up, but if it
was חטאת *chatas* and אשם *asham* blood that got mixed up, that
would invalidate if you brought it on the inside, לא פסיקא ליה
*lo pesika lei*, it's not, it's not categorical.
He's not prepared to say, oh, go ahead, do the inside and
then the outside, because that only works by עולה *olah* and שלמים
*shelamim*, it doesn't work by חטאת *chatas* and an אשם *asham*. Okay.
All right, I think what we'll do, so we don't get too
far ahead, although I'm sure we could really could make it to
the משנה *Mishnah*, we'll end here and we'll pick up tomorrow with
the discussion about Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים *Chachamim* about which blood
gets invalidated when you bring it into the היכל *Heichal*, is it
only חטאת *chatas* blood or is it the blood of any קרבן
*korban*? So we'll pick up with this tomorrow.